{"tossups": [{"question": "During this period, a diplomatic snub toward the ruling government led to the Seikanron debate over a potential invasion of Korea. The Charter Oath laid out the ideals of this period, which proved to be unacceptable to a Satsuma-based group of warriors due to provisions abolishing the practice of feudalism. For ten points, name this period following the Tokugawa Shogunate that featured Western modernizations under a namesake emperor of Japan.", "answer": "<b> Meiji</b> Restoration (accept<b> Meiji</b> Era)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A failed campaign against this man\u2019s troops was bogged down by heavy river quagmires and called the Mud March. This man rose to prominence after the Battle of Seven Pines, where Joseph Johnston was wounded. Shortly after fighting a series of defensive battles at Spotsylvania and the Wilderness, this man spoke at Appomattox Courthouse with Ulysses S. Grant. For ten points, name this commander of the Army of Northern Virginia whose surrender ended the American Civil War.", "answer": "Robert E.<b> Lee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Defense Minister of this country said \u201cit is hard to search for a black cat in a dark room, especially if it\u2019s not there\u201d about the presence of soldiers in a neighboring country. The leader of that neighboring country, Viktor Yanukovych fled to this country after the Euromaidan protests. Soldiers from this country were termed \u201clittle green men\u201d and dismissed as being militiamen despite taking Donbass for this country. For ten points, name this country that annexed Crimea in 2014 under Vladimir Putin.", "answer": "<b> Russia</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "The inspiration for this holiday was an event attended by members of the Wampanoag tribe like Massasoit and Squanto in 1621. For ten points, name this holiday celebrating the first harvest of the Pilgrims in late November.", "answer": "<b> Thanksgiving</b> Day", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A weapon that made use of this object was conceptualized by Hermann Oberth and was studied by Nazi engineers at Hillersleben who predicted they could build it within 100 years. A large black stone in reverence to this object was taken to the Palatine Hill by Elagabalus, whose name derives from a cult surrounding this object. During the siege of Syracuse, Archimedes designed a \u201cdeath ray\u201d that used this body to destroy enemy ships through concentrated heat. Louis the 14th was nicknamed the king of, for ten points, what star?", "answer": "the<b> Sun</b> (prompt on mirrors)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Preludes to this event included the El Encanto arson and a feint towards Baracoa by the<em> Santa Ana</em>. The president allegedly wanted to \u201csplinter the CIA in a thousand pieces\u201d after their failure in this event. Brigade 2506, a force composed of exiles trained in Guatemala, was tasked with carrying out this event, which prompted its target to ally with the Soviet Union. John F. Kennedy authorized, for ten points, what 1961 failed invasion of Cuba?", "answer": "<b> Bay of Pigs</b> invasion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ownership of this location, which forms a national park alongside the adjacent Kata Tjuta, was transfered in a 1985 agreement with the Pitjantjatjara [pit-jant-jat-jara] people. In mythology, this location is the site of a battle between the two serpents Kuniya and Liru. Visitors are now banned from climbing this landmark, as it is the site of a Dreamtime track in the Aboriginal belief system. Ayers Rock is an outdated name of, for ten points, what sandstone formation of the Northern Territory in Australia?", "answer": "<b> Uluru</b> (prompt on Ayers Rock before mentioned)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "These people left artifacts behind in the Ukraine\u2019s largest burial mound, the \u201cBlack Grave.\u201d These people allegedly executed their enemies with the \u201cblood eagle\u201d method and were employed by the Byzantine Empire as the Varangian Guard. These people sacked Lindisfarne and sailed up the Seine River in longships to attack Paris in 845. The colony of Vinland was founded by, for ten points, what seafaring marauders from Scandinavia?", "answer": "<b> Viking</b>s (prompt on Norsemen, Scandinavians, etc.)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In the short-lived first of these wars, a group of regulars lost a quarter of their men to sharpshooters led by Piet Joubert at Laing\u2019s Nek. Between the two of these wars, Alfred Beit helped orchestrate the Jameson Raid in an attempt to overthrow Paul Kruger. Louis Botha and Jan Smuts participated in the second of these wars as leaders of the Transvaal. The British fought in, for ten points, what wars against the namesake Dutch settlers of South Africa?", "answer": "<b> Boer</b> Wars (accept First and/or Second<b> Boer</b> Wars)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Three years after his death, this man\u2019s corpse was dug up, hanged alongside Henry Ireton and John Bradshaw, and beheaded, with his head mounted on a stake above Westminster Hall. This man, whose forces (+) massacred the citizens of Drogheda when they refused to surrender, worked with Thomas Fairfax to win the Battle of (*)</b> Naseby. This man dissolved the Rump Parliament after leading the New Model Army to victory against Charles I. For ten points, name this Parliamentarian commander who became Lord Protector of England.", "answer": "Oliver<b> Cromwell</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In fighting near this city\u2019s San Cosme Gate, future general Ulysses S. Grant disassembled a howitzer and reassembled it in a church, leading to his promotion to captain. The so-called</b> <b>Boy Heroes were killed in this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Boy Heroes were killed in this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>fortress of Chapultepec by US forces led by</b> <b>Winfield Scott. In the (*)</b> Marines\u201d Hymn, this city\u2019s battlefields are referred to as the \u201cHalls of Marines\u201d Hymn, this city\u2019s battlefields are referred to as the \u201cHalls of Montezuma.\u201d For ten points, name this capital city that was taken by the US in the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "<b> Mexico City</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 2013, this country finally released the decades-old Sunderlal Committee report, which investigated police actions during the Telangana Rebellion. The 3rd of June Plan established</b> <b>this country\u2019s western border at the (+)</b> <b>Radcliffe Line. After it achieved independence,</b> <b>this country launched Operation Vijay to reclaim Goa. This country was partitioned from its western neighbor on the request of Muhammad Ali (*) </b> Jinnah\u2019s Muslim League. For ten points, name this former British colony that gained independence in 1947 after the efforts of Jawaharlal Nehru and Mohandas Gandhi.", "answer": "<b> India</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>After Maria Mitchell discovered one of these objects in 1847, Christian VIII of Denmark presented her with a medal. Eight of these objects were discovered by Caroline Herschel, whose brother William discovered the (+) planet Uranus; one of Caroline\u2019s discoveries was found to be periodic in 1819 by Johann Encke, who now names it. One of these objects appears on the (*) </b> Bayeux Tapestry and famously appeared in the years of Mark Twain\u2019s birth and death. For ten points, name these astronomical bodies, the most famous of which is named for Edmund Halley.", "answer": "<b> comet</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A politician from this state was gifted a 1947 Cadillac that was paid for with fifty $25 checks; that man served as the longest-serving Speaker of the House and mentored a man who intimidated his colleagues with (+) \u201cthe treatment.\u201d A politician from this state spoke at the University of Michigan, announcing several progressive policies as part of his (*)</b>\u201cGreat Society\u201d in 1964. For ten points, name this home state of Sam Rayburn and Lyndon B. Johnson, the latter of whom was inaugurated as President in this state\u2019s city of Dallas.", "answer": "<b> Texas</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This company was the defendant in a case, lodged by brothers John and Horace, that determined companies had to operate in the interests of shareholders. The founder of this company launched a failed colony in Aveiro, Brazil, to try to grow cheap (+) rubber and helped promote anti-Semitic views through his pamphlet</b><em><b> The </b><b>International Jew</b></em><b>. This company produced a (*)</b> vehicle every ten seconds at their River Rouge assembly plant; those vehicles came in \u201cany color [...] so long as it is black.\u201d For ten points, name this American car company that produced the Model T.", "answer": "<b> Ford</b> Motor Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}